A Guide to the Papers of William Faulkner 1956-1969
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of William Faulkner, 1956-1969
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7258-l
This collection consists of ca. 330 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection is gift of Mr. Blotner on November 17, 1971.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1956-1969, ca. 330 items, concerning William Faulkner's work with Harvey Breit as co-chairman of the Writer's Committee of President Eisenhower's People to People Program. The content of this collection iluustrates the extent of organizational detail necessary to launch a program such as the People to People Program. The collection is divided into two parts: material concerning promotional details, and letters in answer to Faulkner's appeal to famous writers for support for the program. The letters from notable famous writers are listed separately. Also inlcuded is a copy of an article written by Joseph Blotner concerning Faulkner's role with the committee.
Contents List
- Material Regarding Promotional and Organizational Details of the People to People Program
  - "In and Out of Books," by Harvey Breit, New York Times Book Review1956 Oct 14, Newsclipping
  - People to People News, Vol. 1, no. 2 1956 Oct, Newsletter
  - In response to "In and Out of Books," column 1956 Oct 11-Nov 23, n.d., 32 TLS/8 ALS
  - Report of writer's committee 1956 Nov, TMs (mimeograph), 18 items
  - Circular letters, printed material and miscellaneous 1956, Papers, 15 items
    regarding People to People Program
  - To William Faulkner 1956 Sep 13- 1957 Jan 8, 16 TLS/ALS
    re People to People Program
  - Jean Ennis file 1956-1957, 32 items
    Correspondence & miscellany re People to People Program
- Correspondence from Notable Writers Regarding People to People Program
  - Conrad Aiken to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 3, TLS, 1 p. on 1.
  - William Faulkner to Conrad Aiken 1956 Oct 4, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Newton Arvin to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 30, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faukner to Newton Arvin 1956 Oct 2, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Jacques Barzun to Harvey [Breit] 1956 Oct 5, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Jacques Barzun to Harvey [Breit] 1956 Nov 27, APCS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Saul Bellow to Harvey Breit 1956 Oct 8, Telegram, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Saul Bellow to Jean Ennis 1956 Nov 24, APCS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Saul Bellow to William Faulkner 1956 Jan 7, TLS, 3 p. on 2 l.
    with enclosed questionnaire completed by Saul Bellow
  - John Berryman to William Faukner 1956 Oct 21, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - John Berryman to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 26, TLS 3 p. on 3 l.
    with enclosed questionnaire completed by John Berryman
  - Elizabeth Bishop to Harvey Briet 1956 Oct 18, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Richard Bissell to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 2, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to Richard Bissell 1956 Oct 2, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Louise Bogan to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 26, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Louise Bogan to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 16, TLS, 3 p. on 3 l.
  - Louise Bogan to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 21, APCS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Louise Bogan to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 21, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Van Wyck Brooks to Jean Ennis 1956 Nov 26, APCS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Van Wyck Brooks and Malcolm Cowley to Jean Ennis 1956 [Nov 29], Telegram, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Van Wyck Brooks to Jean Ennis 1957 Jan 9, APCS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Completed questionnaire of Van Wyck Brooks n.d., TMs, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Pearl Buck to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 22, TLS w/env, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Erskine Caldwell to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 26, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to Erskine Caldwell 1956 Oct 2, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to Erskine Caldwell 1956 Oct 11, TLS, 3 p. on 3 l.
    with enclosed questionnaire completed by Erskine Caldwell
  - Truman Capote to William Faulkner [1956 Sep], TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Bruce Catton to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 8, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Bruce Catton to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 7, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Marchette Chute to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 26, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Completed questionnaire of Marchette Chute [1956 Oct], TMs, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Marchette Chute to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 23, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Marchette Chute to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 7, TLS, 1 p. 1 l.
  - Completed questionnaire of Harold Clurman n.d.
  - Malcolm Cowley to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 27, TL, 3 p. on 3 l.
    with enclosed questionnaire completed by Malcolm Cowley
  - Malcolm Cowley to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 6, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - H. L. Davis to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 8, TN, 1 p. on 1 l.
    on bottom TLS, 1956 Oct 11, William Faulkner to H.L. Davis
  - H. L. Davis to William Faulkner 1956 Dec 5, TLS 1 p. on 1 l.
  - H.L. Davis to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 2, TN, 1 p. on 1 l.
    on bottom of TLS, 1957 Jan 2, William Faulkner to H. L. Davis
  - H. L. Davis to William Faulkner n.d., TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - John Dos Passos to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 9, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - John Dos Passos to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 31, TLS, 3 p. on 3 l.
    with enclosed questionnaire completed by John Dos Passos
  - John Dos Passos to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 27, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Willliam Faulkner to John Dos Passos 1957 Jan 2, TLS, ALS
    with note
  - James T. Farrell to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 25, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - James T. Farrell to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 6, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - James T. Farrell to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 18, TL (carbon) and TLS, 8 p. on 8 l. each
  - James T. Farrell to Director, Informational Media Guarantee Bureau 1956 Nov 15, TL (mimeographed), 2 p. on 2 l.
  - James T. Farrell to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 27, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - James T. Farrell to Robert M. Bears 1956 Nov 27, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - James T. Farrell to William Faulkner 1956 Jan 10, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Enda Ferber to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 2, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Edna Ferber to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 2, TLS (copy), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Edna Ferber to Harvey Breit 1956 Oct 2, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to Edna Ferber 1956 Oct 3, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Harvey Breit to Edna Ferber 1956 Oct 9, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Edna Ferber to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 23, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Edna Ferber to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 18, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Robert Fitzgerald to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 28, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to Robert Fitzgerald 1956 Oct 11, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Robert Fitzgerald to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 12, TNS, 1 p on 1 l.
    on bottom of TLS, 1956 Oct 12, William Miller to William Faulkner
  - Shelby Foote to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 6, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Shelby Foote to Jean Ennis 1956 Nov 24, APCS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Waldo Frank to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 25, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Waldo Frank to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 16, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Waldo Frank to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 29, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Erle Stanley Gardner to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 9, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Erle Stanley Gardner to Jean Ennis 1956 Oct 9, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Erle Stanley Gardner to Jean Ennis 1956 Oct 9, TL (carbon), 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Erle Stanley Gardner to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 28
  - Paul Green to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 30, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to Paul Green 1956 Oct 5, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Paul Green to Harvey Breit 1956 Oct 7, Telegram, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Paul Green to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 11, TLS, 1 p. 1 l.
  - Horace Gregory to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 17, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Horace Gregory to William Faulkner 1956 [Nov 22], TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Donald Hall to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 2, TLS, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Donald Hall to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 3, TLS, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to Donald Hall 1956 Oct 3, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Donald Hall To William Faulkner 1956 Oct 14, TLS, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Donald Hall to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 21, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Saxe Commins to Donald Hall 1956 Dec 3, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Saxe Commins to Donald Hall 1956 Dec 13, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Donald Hall to Jean Ennis 1957 Jan 5, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Ralph Hancock to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 3, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
    with enclosed vita of Hancock
  - Ralph Hancock to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 25, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Ralph Hancock to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 11, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Robert Hillyer to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 25, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Robert Hillyer to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 5, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
    with holograph notes on bottom
  - Robert Hillyer to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 23, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to Robert Hillyer 1956 Oct 11, TLS, 3 p. on 3 l.
    with enclosed questionnaire completed by Robert Hillyer
  - Robert Hillyer to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 23, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Inge to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 6, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
    with holograph note on bottom by Inge to Harvey [Breit]
  - William Inge to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 24, TPCS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Inge to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 10, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - MacKinlay Kantor to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 1, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Louis Kronenberger to William Faulkner [1956], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Joseph Wood Krutch to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 25, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to Joseph Wood Krutch 1956 Oct 11, TLS, 3 p. on 3 l.
    with enclosed questionnaire completed by Joseph Wood Krutch
  - Joseph Wood Krutch to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 27, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Joseph Wood Krutch to William Faulkner [1957] Jan 13, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Howard Lindsay to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 23, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Howard Lindsay to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 8, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to Anita Loos 1956 Oct 11, TLS, 3 p. on 3 l.
    with enclosed questionnaire completed by Anita Loos
  - Anita Loos to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 15, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Robert Lowell to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 25, TLS, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Robert Lowell to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 6, TPCS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Robert Lowell to William Faulkner n.d., TNS, 2 p. on 2 1.
    on questionnaire completed by Robert Lowell
  - Archibald MacLeish to William Faulkner [1956] Oct 7, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Archibald MacLeish to William Faulkner [1956] Oct 16, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Dorothy O. Brisson, Secretary to John P. Marquand to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 8, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to Peter Mathiessen 1956 Oct 11, TLS, 3 p. on 3 l.
    with enclosed questionnaire completed by Peter Mathiessen
  - Peter Mathiessen to Jean Ennis n.d., ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Peter Mathiessen to William Faulkner n.d., TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Mary McCarthy to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 12, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Evelyn Shoemaker, Secretary to James Michener to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 15, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Arthur Misner to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 16, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Marianne Moore to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 26, TS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Marianne Moore to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 1, ANS, 3 p. on 3 l.
    on bottom TLS, 1956 Oct 11, William Faulkner to Marianne Moore with enclosed questionnaire completed by Marianne Moore
  - Marianne Moore to Harvey Breit 1956 Nov 27, APCS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Marianne Moore to William Faulkner [1956 Nov], AN, 1 p. on 1 l.
    on bottom TLS, 1956 Nov 20
  - Marianne Moore to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 5, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Lewis Mumford to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 25, ALS, 2 p. to 1 l.
  - Lewis Mumford to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 6, TLS, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Jean Ennis to Lewis Mumford 1956 Oct 11, TLS (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Dudley Nichols to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 25, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Dudley Nichols to Harvey Breit 1956 Oct 7, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Dudley Nichols to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 10, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - George Oppenheimer to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 16, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - George Oppenheimer to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 26, ALS w/env, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - George Oppenheimer to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 21, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Katherine A. Porter to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 26, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Katherine A. Porter to Harvey [Breit] 1956 Oct 4, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Harvey Breit to Katherine A. Porter 1956 Oct 9, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - [William Faulkner] to Merlo Pusey 1956 Oct 11, TL, 3 p. on 3 1.
    with enclosed questionnaire completed by Merlo Pusey
  - Merlo J. Pusey to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 27, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Merlo J. Pusey to William Faulkner [1957] Jan 9, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Merlo J. Pusey to William Faulkner n.d., TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Marc Rangel to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 12, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Elmer Rice to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 3, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Elmer Rice to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 8, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Mark Schorer to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 28, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to Mark Schorer 1956 Oct 1, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Mark Schorer to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 28, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Budd Schulberg to William Faulkner [1956 Nov 6], TLS, 3 p. on 3 l.
    with enclosed questionnaire complete by Budd Schulberg
  - Ramon J. Sender to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 25, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - William Faulkner to Roman J. Sender 1956 Oct 11, TLS, 3 p. on 3 l.
    with enclosed questionnaire completed Ramon J. Sender
  - Ramon Sender to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 16, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Ramon Sender to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 25, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - John Steinbeck to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 3, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to John Steinbeck 1956 Oct 5, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - John Steinbeck to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 28, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Saxe Commins to John Steinbeck 1956 Dec 3, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - John Steinbeck to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 11, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Frederick M. Stern to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 24, TLS 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Frederick M. Stern to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 21, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Frederick M. Stern to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 8, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Irving Stone to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 9, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Irving Stone to [William Faulkner] 1957 Jan 9, TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
  - Phil Stong to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 25, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Phil Stong to William Faulkner [1956 Oct], TNS, 1 p. on 1 l.
    on bottom, TLS, 1956 Oct 1, William Faulkner to Phil Stong
  - Phil Stong to William Faulkner 1956 Nov 21, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Phil Song to William Faulkner [1957] Jan 5, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Styron to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 15, ALS, 3 p. on 3 l.
    with enclosed questionnaire completed by William Styron
  - George Tabori to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 7, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Allen Tate to William Faulkner 1957 Oct 6, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Lionel Trilling to Harvey Breit 1956 Oct 8, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Jane Gray, Secretary to Lionel Trilling to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 8, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to Gore Vidal 1956 Oct 3, TL (carbon), 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Gore Vidal to William Faulkner [1956], TLS, 2 p. on 2 l.
    with enclosed questionnaire completed by Gore Vidal
  - Robert Penn Warren to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 19, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Anthony West to William Faulkner [1956 Nov 29], TL, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Memo, Anthony West to William Faulkner [1956 Nov 29], TMsS, 3 p. on 3 l.
  - E. B. White to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 5, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Richard Wilbur to William Faulkner [1956], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Richard Wilbur to William Faulkner [1957] Jan 10, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Thornton Wilder to William Faulkner 1956 Oct 5, ALS, 2 p. on 1 l.
  - Thornton Wilder to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 4, ALS, 4 p. on 2 l.
  - William Carlos Williams to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 24, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William Faulkner to William C. Williams 1956 Oct 11, TLS, 3 p. on 3 l.
    with enclosed questionaire completed by William C. Williams
  - William C. Williams to William Faulkner [1956] Nov 24, TPC, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - William C. Williams to William Faulkner 1957 Jan 8, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Edmund Wilson to William Faulkner 1956 Sep 25, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - Edmund Wilson to William Faulkner, 1 p. on 1 l. 1956 Nov 21, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.
  - "William Faulkner. Committee Chairman" 1969, TMsS (carbon), 24 p. on 24 l.
    an article by Joseph Blotner